okay good morning doctor huh
let's meditate you want to get ready
turn off your phone
relax your mouth relax your eyes
tighten your stomach a little bit
relax your fingers shoulders back
for headstart
remember that smile keep that smile
and then we'll start to follow the
breath deep exhale at the end of that
cuz I'll push out a little bit extra
no I'm sorry mm morning state of mind
Diamond Mountain beautiful morning
Sunday Easter state of mind peaceful
calm not too busy from the day
now please look ahead into this week
we're all going back to our normal
schedule family and work we've pushed
off maybe nine or ten days of work and
there's big jobs we have to deal with
when we go maybe there are personal
issues with people their theory of
diamond mountain retreat center is that
those people will give you trouble are
those problems that come to you at home
this is too far away for them to come
here but now this week we will go back
we can't avoid them and difficult
situations difficult people so choose
one of these challenges you can expect
them in this week when you come home and
watch how it makes your breathing speed
up make your heartbeat speed up when you
begin to you begin to lose the diamond
mountain morning mind and just observe
especially with challenges people
problems work problems how your retreat
mine is going to melt away in the next
day or two
it happens to all retreatants in the
world in history we would like to keep
them retreat state of mind but as soon
as were driving to the airport we start
to lose it and our mind gets more busy
and especially with the problem people
problem problems at work family problems
we the mind gets stirred up like the
wind coming across the ocean
then what we've learned this week about
negative emotions feeling nervous about
the week that's coming up maybe almost
upset already about difficult people we
have to meet and sorry Davis said the
nose needs a face without a body the
nose by itself cannot walk around the
room the nose has to be attached to her
face and all kinds of nervousness about
this coming week apprehension worry
wanting to avoid people difficult
situations they all are based like our
nose they're all based on our face and
the face is misunderstanding where these
things come from me feel helpless
because we don't know what to do
but that's misunderstanding so I'd like
you to try to pick one person or one
difficult situation coming up this week
and try to think about the pen and try
to think about what seeds did I make
that created this person or this
situation what did I do this year or
last month similar thing to somebody
else
this created seeds now this week though
Ceaser
opening so check what little things you
may be doing karma second law of karma
it always expands so if I have a
difficult person or a difficult
situation I must be doing something
similar first law of karma but much
smaller second law of karma so try to
guess what you're doing yourself to
create this yelling husband in the
kitchen who's coming to you this week
last time
try to think of some good seeds you
might plant even on the way home that
could help fix this situation
so in general we have a choice we can do
the four powers we can it made our
mistakes to somebody we can examine our
negative seeds and behavior we can try
to turn off those seeds but I think most
of us we respond better to positive
seeds positive actions so let's try that
with the problem person this week or the
situation this week let's think about
positive seeds we could land if we have
someone who is jealous of us giving us
trouble then instead of trying to stop
our jealousy seeds which we do have we
could focus on rejoicing in other
people's good qualities which is a
happier way to change those seeds so try
to think about a little plan for this
week how to plant some fresh happy seeds
that are the opposite of the problem
you're going home to or challenges
you're going home to here we go
and now place three deep breaths without
open your eyes three deep breaths I'll
send the Karma of this good week of hard
work we worked really hard here and send
it to the world as a gift on your breath
nice thoughtful 3xs
then slowly open your eyes take a
stretchy
any questions comments ideas things you
think might help other people
thank you for this beautiful meditation
I had a little insight if nothing has a
nature of its own
then seeds must be empty as well then is
it possible to seeds that I perceive as
negative to shift my perception and
think of them as positive to really
experience them as positive yeah it's an
interesting question if seeds are empty
then they are like the pen and the seed
which I see as a dog toy now if I had
better seeds under the seeds I should be
able to see those seeds as positive
seeds and I think the best it's true it
is true and I think a good example is
people that hurt us you know in the past
for example so oftentimes we can point
to a time in the past when we had a big
breakup or somebody bus got angry at us
at work and we lost our job or him
we had a big health problem you know and
our whole life up to now we had seeds to
see it as a problem and then if our
seeds improved history gets rewritten ok
it's called what is revisionism
historical we could call it seed
revisionism and you start to revise the
story of your life you know then it's
not like this boy hurt me or this girl
hurt me or this place fired me it's this
Buddha gave me a chance to go higher and
I got a better partner
and I got a better job I applied for 30
diamond jewelry store jobs after I
finished my geology degree I applied for
30 jobs in jewelry stores and I remember
going for one of the interviews and the
jewelry store owner told me to wait
because a mother came in with a small
daughter and they put her on the Shelf
the counter and he took a big gun and he
put it on her ear you know had the girls
like smiling and and mommy's like saying
don't worry it's not gonna hurt you know
and she's okay mom
and then he goes you know and then she
goes and they couldn't do the second one
she was screaming so much then I I'm
waiting for my interview you know and
I'm like I can't do this to little girls
you know and I just left the store so
then I I thought oh I have bad seats you
know I went to 30 jewelry stores nobody
wants to her nobody wants somebody who
never worked in diamonds they don't know
if you're honest then I I met my future
business partner and and we built the
world's largest diamond jewelry coming
and so I always bow down to those old
Bad Seeds for 30 rejections in the
jewelry stores you know and I'm like
maybe those were good seats you know so
yeah seats are empty like a pen and as
you go on they can shift and you can
rewrite your life and that's a big part
of Tantra that's a big part of the
vagina practice any other question
- you like Thank You Keisha a lot for
teaching I won't say what happened with
me in this thin days when I was a kid I
watched the sky and I had a dream or
wish or desire to stop all wars to stop
being people being angry and after my
maybe 12
then slowly realized that it is not
possible and when when I became older I
start thinking that everything comes
itself happens itself and we cannot do
anything we cannot change it and you
know yesterday in meditation actor
connected with me myself three or four
years old I understand that it is
possible I thank you for the feeling you
know now and became the whole United you
know that I'm so happy with that and
also I met the book in 9 2016
April when I was travelling with mr.
norburg of and sometimes I think that he
has a master he give me from one part of
teaching as you said yesterday the river
all rivers go to ocean
so you see em here second time I come
from Muslim country and I have I am a
sling and I have a dream connect all
religious and all maybe not religious
all people Christian because we are part
Christian Orthodox part Muslim country
Buddhist people others as unity who can
connect and help all human beings so
maybe all beings all over the world so
thank you for teaching stay with us
thank you
[Music]
[Applause]
all right let me tell one story okay
then I'll come back and this is it also
came to me the same thing because today
is Easter this is a big holiday for the
Christians and we have two big two
holidays you have to go to church the
churches are full this morning
then the people don't come back and tell
Christmas and so we used to go every
Easter and I remember the first time I
went to our church and I still go there
sometimes it's in Phoenix and my mom I
remember she she brought me down I
remember which seat and she said you get
on your knees you know and I'm like why
because you never get on your knees in
real life right unless you're watching
the floor or something and so and she
said hold your hands like this you know
and then I said okay mom what do I do
and she said you pray for everybody and
I'm like what's that mean
let's pray and she said you think about
someone you love and then you send them
good thoughts you wish them good health
happy life and I thought okay mom I can
do that and she said don't forget you
have to do for everybody and I'm like
okay mom and I remember closing my eyes
you know like Easter and uhm okay let's
see I'll start with mom I hope you're
healthy I hope everything's happy I hope
you're fine you know and then I did my
dad you know I hope you're good I hope
you're happy
then I had three brothers I did my
brothers then she's like hitting me on
the shoulder you know I'm like wow you
know and she said we have to go and I'm
like I'm not finished you said everybody
and she said well you can't really do
everybody you know and I said I was just
getting to our aunt
uncles and she said yeah but you you
can't actually pray for everyone it's
not really possible you know but you're
supposed to try I said I finished like
five people you know there's a seven
five billion left at that time and she
said well we have to go they're gonna
close it to her she know and then as you
get older maybe it's the same in Islam
and you say okay it's impossible or I
cannot stop war for example it's it's
not gonna be possible I think around age
16 you say it's not gonna work you know
prayers don't work you pray for people
they die anyway and you kind of quit in
your mind you say this is not gonna be
possible and I can't stop war I went to
jail briefly during the Vietnam War and
I because I wanted to try to stop the
world but it then later I decided it
just doesn't work you know you can't do
it and then in DC I we kept talking
about being a virus you know becoming a
virus so if you solve your problems next
week by planting the opposite seeds okay
so if I have someone who's mean to me
every day and instead of talking to them
instead of fighting with them I just try
to change my seats then first of all
they change second I become happier all
the time
third people start to notice I'm
different than I was before and maybe
not before they asked me to teach them a
CIA course one
okay and then I become a virus so you
know I teach John then John teach Connie
and John Akane teach Peter and my son
Peter must go to Kiev and teach hundreds
of people and then I can't go around the
world and I can't really pray for
everybody but I can be a virus you know
I can start a I can start an explosion I
can be there first
what do you call ground zero I can be
the beginning of the virus and then if
John is successful then Connie will want
to learn about it and if John and Connie
are successful then Peter and Masha will
want to learn about it and then if Peter
and Masha look happy
then their students who want to learn
about it and then it's just spreads by
itself you know and I think in this way
just recently I was thinking about it
and this is my little Easter sermon okay
you can change the whole world
you can pray for the whole world you can
affect each person and you're the method
is to become a happy person and a
successful person inside successful and
outside successful and then people will
copy you and then in this way you pray
for all people you see I mean so my mom
was right but she was also wrong okay
cool
all right Daniel had her come in so the
fourth law of karma says that if you
plant a seat then you must see the
result and I'm just wondering how to
marry that idea with the fact that a
Buddha has seeds that will never ripen
yeah I don't know it's unexplainable by
the way Tim that last part about the mom
taking me to church I'd like to add it
to the class 7 or something like that
wherever it goes the body thought
bodhichitta may be class 8
I'd like to add it to the official video
for the teacher yeah I just yeah let's
stick it in there somewhere
this is technically long morning yeah
okay here's here's Daniels question so
suppose I heard someone then I do the
four powers and what's the diamond
cutter suture thing what will happen if
I heard someone I'm supposed to have a
car accident but I do therefore parts I
promise not especially I promise not to
do it again yeah the diamond cutter says
I will get a headache or if you do a
good confession the seed will never open
so then what happened to universal
justice you know I'm supposed to have
something bad happened to me and in DC I
would teach it two ways I think it's
interesting first when we teach the four
powers which is decide one or two we say
this is how to stop your bad seed
because once you teach somebody about
the seeds carefully the first question
an intelligent person asks is okay I
understand
seeds and the pen makes sense and I
understand the ten good deeds but what
do I do about my old bad C's is there
something I can do about my old bad seed
this is like halfway to level one or
towards the end of number one you start
to get this in your discussion group
right and those are the most intelligent
people they they already figured out
a plan for the rest of their life
they'll try to not make bad things but
they are wondering how to deal with
their old Betsy's and then at DCI we
teach them game purg a game Peggy
so at the beginning in DC I we teach
them oh yeah you can make your old bad
seats go away then the that question
came from the more intelligent ones then
the more intelligent ones of the more
intelligent ones during level two they
will say wait a minute you said fourth
law of karma you know if you do
something you have to have a result then
when they start when they're thinking
reaches this level we start to talk to
them about putting a watermelon seed on
this lectern and putting water on it and
making it warm and it will actually open
like if a seed packet gets wet for a few
days it will open inside the paper but
then it dies for lack of nutrition lack
of nutrients right so when we get to
that when we get them more intelligent
more intelligent question then we tell
them about the diamond cutter Sutra you
will have a a bad result it will open
and that's the way you kill it you force
it to open like a premature baby okay it
comes out under nourished it's too small
to survive and then it dies then the
intelligent of the intelligent of the
intelligent they'll say but wait a
minute it's not just that bad these make
bad results they're supposed to make
corresponding bad results if I kill
someone I have to die it's not like I
can get a headache you know so how do
you answer that and and then I think
that's where your mind is that right now
and it's that the good there's a special
good karma seed well let me put it this
way
follow me okay stay with me cuz you're
you're at the advanced question stage
how do you make a good seed grow faster
and better yeah coffee man is she
somebody over total fourth chapter the
next Eva making well so just be happy
about what you did okay now if you enjoy
suffering how do you make a bad seed
grow fast and well yeah you're hot
yeah the easy answer is be happy you did
something bad
but the deeper answer is the way to get
a bad seed to grow faster and bigger is
to misunderstand it and that's what the
wheel of life is based on links number
eight and nine make the bad seeds grow
bigger and faster because you
misunderstand them okay
so during for powers you're not just
promising not to do something again the
four powers itself shows you understand
seeds you see part of the reason why the
four powers works is you wouldn't do
them if you didn't understand this okay
so it's not just promising not to repeat
it out here it's the raw karmic strength
dope right we called chatter Bala Bala
in Sanskrit the power of understanding
the seeds okay so the seed to die
because you killed someone if you treat
it with the for power
and a heavy dose of chemo you know
understanding chemo it mixes with the
bad seed and it helps destroy it okay
got it so it if it grew back for power
that would break the law of karma cool
think about it
one more question maybe if anyone has
you guys got my Clarkson my round corner
Thank You Ashley
no you always ask hard question I gonna
do that's me I don't don't be like word
okay there is one question I still
didn't ganda didn't understand and I
didn't find the answer yet in your
teachings all they say courses about
consciousness about our mind if you say
that everything has to have a cause and
there is no creator of of this world
then then what start our mind if it if
it's last forever then God could be
inevitable and could be forever so what
is the difference here okay good
question I remember I had a talk with
Ken Rinpoche you know we had lots of
talks like this and he said one day he
said Cedric to me science
he said I don't understand this science
stuff and it was so comforting to have
him tell me he didn't understand
something
and because I went to Princeton I
graduated with honors I thought it was
really smart and then when I got to the
his house to live with him he treat me
like I'm an idiot you know and it was
very uncomfortable I'm used to getting
awards and going to the white house and
here's this person
everything I say is stupid and it was
very very unpleasant and all my friends
told me why you why you go live in that
it's a call to white trash town poor
white people very poor white people they
have two cars in their backyard broken
cars and you know they're poor and they
never brush their teeth they're like how
can you stay there
you know I said sometimes I don't know
and this guy yells at me all day and he
tells me I don't understand anything so
he asked me so where does the world come
from you know San Reba in science where
does the world come from I'm like I'll
tell you and thanks for asking and
that's before I knew him very well you
never argue with Ken ribbity because he
always wins he can say the sky is not
blue and he can prove it and you will
fail it's better just to shut up and
clean the toilets so anyway I said well
he said what's the main idea of science
you know nowadays I heard in the
monastery from uniden they I tried to
teach them science and I think it's I
mean it's okay but the foundation of
science is mistaken buddhism is correct
science is not correct so it's a little
you know I think the younger she should
understand I think it it's wrong the
basis of science is wrong
so anyway
I said well he said what's the main
principle soul right what's that the
principle idea PA all right what's the
principle idea yeah everything has a
cause he goes oh that's great that's
just like dependent origination you know
everything has a cause nothing happens
without a cause you know and I feel
really proud of my country because
America invented all science maybe they
teach you that in your country or if
when you're in the school in America
when you're young it seems like
Americans invented everything I'm sure
in China you know paper gunpowder what's
the other two ceramics for I mean the
Chinese invented it 5,000 years before
the Americans but we don't we don't hear
that in the school so we're like oh yeah
yeah that's science
and we discovered it near Princeton
Einstein Institute for Advanced Study
everything has a cause you know and he
said oh and that's the main idea of
science and we said yeah I said yeah and
he's oh I should have known
later I would know this conversation is
a trap but I feel very proud I'm like
yeah you know you have any other
questions and he's like yes so how did
things start you know and I said well
everything has to have a cause therefore
there must be a first cause okay
creation there must be a first cause
because everything has to have a cause
therefore there must be a beginning by
the way and that's Sciences mistake
that's the big mistake okay you got to
think about it so I said everything has
to have a beginning and he said well
what's the beginning of everything in
science
you know what's the beginning of
everything I said oh thanks for asking
there was a big bang and all matter was
in the size of a thumbnail all the
universe
compressed you know shank in the size of
your thumbnail all the planets all the
stars was in the compressed into this
much energy and then one day it blew up
you know and and that's the first cause
of all planets all stars all people all
birds everything okay
that's the first moment that's the first
cause and he goes oh like wow I'm so
grateful you explain science to me then
he goes but what was the cause of that
cause you know and I'm like then I'm
thinking like nowadays they say the bang
before the Big Bang Big Bang pre bang
you know then I'm like well well that
one didn't have a car so he said but
science foundation idea everything has a
course yeah except everything then I'm
like
yeah he says get out of here
you know his get out of my room don't
tell me stupid things you know get out
of here hey get out of here this is so
ridiculous so what do you do who asked
me a question oh yeah yeah so there
cannot be a first cause you see I was
brought up as a child in the class
especially science class and they said
if you can find the first cause of
something you found the cause but if you
spend five minutes with Ken Rinpoche he
will explain to you easily that there
cannot be a first cause okay
it's not possible okay it's not possible
if there's a first cause that doesn't
have a cause then then science is
completely all science is wrong okay
good is that better
I if you want the easy explanation it's
called the spaghetti noodle okay your
mind is like a long spaghetti noodle
that has no beginning and no end so to
me it helps to make a picture in my mind
there's a black space and then Mueller
spaghetti company started a spaghetti
noodle and it went all the way back in
time and it keeps going they keep making
it longer and then into the future the
spaghetti noodle goes okay like that and
two things about that spaghetti well
three things okay four things number one
it does not have a beginning it cannot
have a beginning because a cause needs a
cause and in Buddhism all changing
things are both causes and results all
changing things are both causes and
results okay
when you yelled at your kids that was a
cause of your husband yelling but it was
also a result of yelling at your husband
last week before okay so there is no
beginning to your mind it's not possible
if you say there's a beginning then
you're saying something can happen from
nothing but we know come on sing it
nothing comes from nothing nothing never
could but some time in my youth or
childhood I must think good that's the
best song from Austria
yeah then the spaghetti noodle second so
first it has no beginning so you know
sometimes picture it in your mind black
space spaghetti noodle goes back with no
beginning cannot have a beginning okay
not possible if it was cause they cannot
have a beginning then goes into the
future endlessly then I'm gonna give a
naughty example which is very unusual
there's a and in abhidharma okay I'll
call I'll be Dumber then I won't get in
trouble him most human beings in their
life in the spaghetti noodle of this
life they have their first sexual
experience you know and and there's a
mark on the spaghetti noodles somebody
took a pen and mark the spaghetti noodle
before that you're a virgin okay boy or
girl and then after that you're not you
know and and that's a mark that most
people can make a mark and say ok I
remember the day I remember where I was
you know and they draw a line and after
that you're a different kind of person
and before that you're virgin okay so
that's one mark on your spaghetti noodle
why am I talking about that
yeah for for all living beings the first
direct perception of emptiness is the
mark on the spaghetti noodle it's the
only one okay either you're an aria or
you're not that's all that really
matters okay either you're an aria or
you're not
it is so emptiness directly or you
didn't okay and that's what you call so
people who didn't see it or emptyness
virgins good and people who did see it I
don't know what you call emptiness
non-virgin okay and there's a line on
the spaghetti noodle there's a second
line who wants to tell me yeah our heart
which means what you don't suffer no
more pain okay person with pain endless
no beginning come up to this point draw
a line and then after that no pain ever
okay so those are the big spaghetti
noodle marks what's the ultimate mark my
body changed a living diamond the whole
body changed their living time I can
split into multiple bodies I can help
billions of planets at the same time
okay cool yeah so that's how you have to
think about it okay remember the
conversation think about the
conversation with Cameron Benji okay and
it will be clear to you okay it'll come
clear to you